♪Confessing to the moon in the rustling wind back then♪
♪จันทร์เคยแจ่มกระจ่าง♪
♪Like a boat being swallowed up among the cities♪
♪พลันแปรเป็นทะเลคลั่ง♪
♪Watching the flowers fall in unease worries and troubles fill my mind♪
♪ตระหนกฟังเสียงบุปผาโรย♪
♪Am I going to where I want♪
♪ทุกที่ที่ไป♪
♪To stay or to leave you decide♪
♪ด้วยการไปหรืออยู่ของเจ้า♪
♪Nations are different♪
♪ปฐพีกับแผ่นดินก็ต่างกัน♪
♪One without desire is one that is not alive♪
♪ฟ้าดินไร้ใจ♪
♪Looking at the sky side by side♪
♪ร่วมเคียงชมนภา♪
♪We've gotten closer with time♪
♪กาลเข้มข้นกว่าเวลา♪
♪One glance the city of Chang'an is bare♪
♪มองผ่านปราดเดียว♪
♪Among the ridiculous people and things is me♪
♪ในเรื่องราวเหลวไหลของผู้คน♪
=Episode 48=
=ตอนที่ 48=
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
I have failed you.
บ่าวเฒ่าไร้สามารถ
I couldn't find Official Han.
หาใต้เท้าหานไม่พบพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
It doesn't matter.
ไม่เป็นไร
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
Perhaps it's better to take a day off
ถ้าอย่างไรวันนี้ทรงพักสักวัน
from the imperial court meeting.
อย่าเสด็จไปประชุมเช้าเลยพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
I must attend
การประชุมเช้าวันนี้
the imperial court meeting today.
ข้าต้องไป
Has Yu'er left the palace?
อวี๋เอ๋อร์ออกจากวังหรือยัง
As per your order,
ทำตามที่ฝ่าบาทรับสั่ง
I reminded her this morning
พอเช้ากระหม่อมก็เตือนนาง
to send her sister back for a proper burial.
ให้พาพี่สาวกลับไปกลบฝังให้ดี
Judging by the time now,
ตอนนี้คิดว่า
she should be on her way.
น่าจะอยู่ระหว่างทางแล้ว
It's good to know that.
ไปแล้วก็ดี
There will be a fierce battle today.
วันนี้จะมีศึกดุเดือด
I don't have
ข้าเอง
the strength
ไม่หลงเหลือเรี่ยวแรงที่จะ
to keep her safe.
ไปปกป้องนางแล้ว
But that place
ทว่าที่นั่น
is populated
คนมาก
and full of secret tunnels.
ทางลับก็มาก
A complicated structure
ยิ่งวุ่นวาย
gives her a better chance of survival.
ก็ยิ่งมีโอกาส
She is alert.
ประสาทสัมผัสนางว่องไว
Not to mention Yan Xiu is with her.
แถมยังมีเหยียนซิวอยู่ข้างกาย
I believe
ข้าเชื่อว่า
she will survive this ordeal.
นางจะต้องรอดจากเภทภัยครั้งนี้ได้
Huaizhi.
หวยจื้อ
After I've attended the imperial court meeting,
ไว้ข้าไปประชุมแล้ว
take your retirement letter
เจ้าจงถือหนังสือลาออก
and leave this palace.
แล้วไปจากที่นี่เสีย
Your Majesty!
ฝ่าบาท
You've thought of an escape plan
พระองค์ทรงคิดหาทางถอย
for all of us.
ให้แก่พวกเราทุกคน
But what will you do?
แล้วพระองค์จะทำอย่างไรเล่าพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
There is no way for me to get out.
ข้าไม่มีทางถอย
There was never an escape plan for me.
ไม่เคยมีมาก่อน
Your Majesty!
ฝ่าบาท
Yanzhi.
เยียนจือ
Ruoling and I
ข้ากับรั่วหลิง
are here to see you off.
มาส่งเจ้าเป็นครั้งสุดท้าย
You could have gone anywhere
พวกเจ้าจะไปที่ไหนไม่ไป
but this place.
ดันเลือกกลับมาที่นี่
Hand over the posthumous edict.
ส่งพินัยกรรมออกมา
It's what's best for both of us.
เจ้ารอด ข้าก็รอด
When did they install this contraption?
เวลาแบบนี้ทำไมยังมีกลไกมากมายอยู่อีก
Search for them!
ยังไม่รีบไปหาให้ข้าอีก
Yes!
ขอรับ
My sister foresaw this?
พี่ใหญ่คาดการณ์ได้ตั้งแต่แรก
Come with me.
มากับข้า
What about my sister?
แล้วพี่ใหญ่จะทำอย่างไร
This place is safe.
ที่นี่ปลอดภัยมาก
We'll come back for her
รีบเผด็จศึกให้เสร็จ
when the job is done.
แล้วค่อยมาฝังศพนาง
Let's go.
ไป
Why isn't Official Li here yet?
ทำไมใต้เท้าหลี่ยังไม่มาอีก
I don't know.
ไม่รู้เหมือนกัน
Before we parted ways yesterday,
เมื่อวานตอนที่แยกกัน
he promised he would be here today.
ตกลงกันแล้วว่าจะมาหนิ
Perhaps he's ill?
หรือว่าจะไม่สบาย
You...
เจ้า
How dare you drug me?
นี่เจ้ากล้าวางยาพ่อเชียวหรือ
One mistake
เจ้ารู้หรือไม่ว่าเดินผิดหนึ่งก้าว
will lead to countless more.
ก็ผิดทุกก้าว
Yes.
ใช่
I made a mistake back then.
ตอนนั้นข้าผิดไปแล้วครั้งหนึ่ง
So this time,
ดังนั้นครั้งนี้
I won't make the same mistake again.
จะผิดอีกไม่ได้
What's wrong?
มีอะไร
It's here.
เป็นที่นี่
My grandfather once
ตอนนั้นท่านปู่
took my sister and I to this place.
เคยพาข้ากับพี่ใหญ่มาทางนี้
The exit...
ทางออก
The exit is over there.
ทางออกอยู่ตรงนั้น
You've regained your memory.
เจ้าจำทุกอย่างได้แล้วจริง ๆ หรือ
I will finish what my grandfather started
เรื่องที่ท่านปู่เคยทำค้างคาไว้
years ago.
ข้าจะเป็นคนสานต่อเอง
Your Majesty.
ทูลฝ่าบาท
Qiu Ziliang is full of lies and deceptions.
ฉิวจื่อเหลียงปกปิดเบื้องสูงเบื้องล่าง
He has no regard for the laws,
ทำตัวเหนือกฎหมาย
stashed weapons illegally,
ลอบสะสมอาวุธ
and hired his own private troops.
เพาะสร้างกองทหาร
He assassinated two princes,
ลอบสังหารสองท่านอ๋อง
our Empress,
หนึ่งพระสนม
and the four Ministers.
สี่เสนา
He was removed from his titles,
แม้ปลดจากทุกตำแหน่ง
but the people are not satisfied with his punishment.
แต่ก็ไม่อาจคลายความโกรธแค้นประชา
His crimes are beyond unspeakable!
ความผิดประดายากจะบรรยายได้หมด ฝ่าบาท
We request for Your Majesty to pass wise judgment
วอนฝ่าบาททรงสอบสวน
on the Qiu Ziliang and his ilk.
ฉิวจื่อเหลียงในฐานหัวหน้าพรรคขันที
Their punishment shall serve as a reminder to the world.
เพื่อเชือดไก่ให้ลิงดูด้วย
How should I proceed with the investigation?
แล้วจะให้สอบสวนอย่างไร
This is the name list of those in cahoot with Qiu Ziliang.
นี่คือรายชื่อพวกพ้องของขันทีแซ่ฉิว
Please have a look.
ขอฝ่าบาททอดพระเนตร
(Liu Zhixuan, Liang Zhihuan)
(รายชื่อพวกพ้องของขันทีแซ่ฉิว)
Qiu Ziliang surrendered yesterday,
ฉิวจื่อเหลียงเพิ่งถูกจับเมื่อวาน
(Name list of Qiu Ziliang's followers) and the name list is already presented to me.
วันนี้ก็มีรายชื่อเสียแล้ว
Your efficiency in handling the matter
ประสิทธิภาพในการทำงานของพวกท่าน
has impressed me deeply.
ชวนให้ข้าตกตะลึงดีแท้
We request for Your Majesty to punish these villains
วอนฝ่าบาททรงลงอาญาคนชั่วอย่างเด็ดขาด
and cleanse the Imperial Court of their corruption.
ชำระราชสำนัก
There is nowhere to run now.
จะหนีอีกหรือไม่
Did Prince Guang
ท่านอ๋องกวง
send you after me?
สั่งให้พวกเจ้ามาหรือ
I still can't believe Prince Guang
ถึงตอนนี้ข้ายังไม่อยากจะเชื่อ
is actually an evil villain.
ว่าที่แท้ท่านอ๋องกวงจะเป็นคนเลว
A villain?
คนเลว
He was never a villain.
ท่านอ๋องไม่เคยเป็นคนเลว
Qi Yan is the real problem here.
ตัวปัญหาที่แท้จริงคือฉีเยี่ยน
You have no right to slander His Majesty.
เจ้าไม่มีคุณสมบัติจะวิจารณ์ฝ่าบาท
You may open
หากไม่เชื่อละก็
the scroll
เจ้าก็สามารถเปิด
if you don't believe us.
ม้วนภาพที่อยู่ด้านหลังเจ้าออกมาดูได้
Find out who is
ว่าตอนนั้นอดีตฮ่องเต้
the rightful heir to the throne.
ต้องการมอบบัลลังก์ให้แก่ผู้ใด
You want the posthumous edict.
เจ้าต้องการพินัยกรรมใช่หรือไม่
Then come and get it.
อยากได้ก็เข้ามาแย่งสิ
I never like
แต่ไหนแต่ไรมาข้าไม่เคยชอบ
using violence.
การฆ่าฟัน
Not to mention
ที่สำคัญเจ้ายังเป็น
you are Miss Yanzhi's little sister.
น้องสาวแท้ ๆ ของแม่นางเยียนจือ
Hand over the posthumous edict.
ดังนั้นส่งพินัยกรรมมาเถอะ
I'll let you go.
แล้วข้าจะปล่อยพวกเจ้าไป
I promise you won't be hurt.
รับรองจะไม่ทำร้ายแม้แต่น้อย
It belongs to Prince Guang
ที่สำคัญมันเป็นของ
all along.
ของท่านอ๋องตั้งแต่แรก
The Late Emperor ordered Han Yue to give it to
ตอนนั้นอดีตฮ่องเต้ให้หานเยว่
your grandfather.
มอบแก่ท่านปู่ของเจ้า
He wanted your grandfather to hand it to Prince Guang.
ให้ท่านปู่เจ้ามอบต่อท่านอ๋อง
How is it yours
ทำไมพอถึงมือเจ้า
simply because you have it?
ถึงได้กลายเป็นของของเจ้าไปได้เสียล่ะ
Unfortunately, I am a stubborn person.
น่าเสียดายที่ข้าเป็นคนดื้อเอามาก ๆ
It'd be great if I would hand it over.
หากข้าอยากให้ก็เรื่องหนึ่ง
But since you plan to take it from me,
แต่ถ้าเจ้าคิดจะแย่ง
not a chance.
ก็เสียใจด้วย
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
After Qiu Ziliang's execution,
ฉิวจื่อเหลียงถูกจับ
the Shencai Army became leaderless.
ทัพเสินไฉไร้ผู้นำ
They are without a goal.
สภาพดั่งทรายที่กระจาย
We should select a new General-in-Chief
สมควรจะเลือก
as soon as possible.
แม่ทัพใหญ่คนใหม่โดยเร็ว
This is the name list of people
นี่คือรายชื่อที่พวกกระหม่อมร่วมกัน
we recommend.
เสนอให้คัดเลือก
Please have a look.
เชิญฝ่าบาททอดพระเนตร
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
This is the name list.
นี่คือรายชื่อ
Please have a look.
เชิญฝ่าบาททอดพระเนตร
(Han Ding)
(รายชื่อแม่ทัพใหญ่คนใหม่)
Summon Hand Ding.
เบิกหานติ้งเข้าเฝ้า
I,
กระหม่อม
Han Ding,
หานติ้ง
greet Your Majesty.
ถวายบังคมฝ่าบาท
Do you wish
เจ้าอยากเป็น
to be the Shencai Army's General-in-Chief?
แม่ทัพใหญ่ทัพเสินไฉอย่างนั้นหรือ
You leave me with no choice.
เจ้าบังคับข้าเองนะ
My sister...
พี่ใหญ่
I designed the secret chamber.
ห้องลับข้าเป็นคนออกแบบ
I would surely know
พวกเจ้าวางกับดักไว้
if you modified it.
มีหรือข้าจะไม่รู้
But I pity Miss Yanzhi.
น่าสงสารแต่แม่นางเยียนจือ
She is already dead,
คนก็ตายไปแล้ว
but she still can't have peace.
ยังไม่อาจกลบฝังอย่างสงบ
What is it that you want?
เจ้าคิดจะทำอะไร
The same as always.
ยังคงคำเดิม
Hand over the posthumous edict.
ส่งพินัยกรรมออกมา
Then I'll leave,
ข้าไป
and you can have her back.
พวกเจ้าไปฝังศพ
Don't make me do it.
อย่าบังคับข้าเลย
Ruoling.
รั่วหลิง
Fine.
ได้
My sister comes before anything.
ไม่มีอะไรที่สำคัญไปกว่าพี่ใหญ่
(The heir shall be Prince Guang, the thirteen prince.)
(นับแต่ข้าครองราชย์ อยู่ในตำแหน่งมาเก้าปี รู้สึกอับอายโกรธแค้น...)
Great.
ดีมาก
We're even now.
เจ๊ากันแล้ว
Let's go.
ไป
Sorry.
ขอโทษด้วย
I miscalculated.
ข้าไม่รอบคอบเอง
This isn't your fault.
เจ้าอย่าตำหนิตัวเองเลย
The posthumous edict
พินัยกรรมนี้
was meant for Prince Guang anyway.
เดิมต้องมอบให้ท่านอ๋องกวงอยู่แล้ว
His Majesty told me something
ฝ่าบาททรงบอกเรื่องหนึ่งให้ข้ารู้
I couldn't tell my sister.
ข้าไม่ทันบอกต่อพี่ใหญ่
She didn't know,
ดังนั้นพี่ใหญ่จึงไม่รู้
nor did Prince Guang.
ท่านอ๋องกวงก็ไม่รู้
Take my sister with you
เจ้ารีบพาพี่ใหญ่
and leave.
ไปจากที่นี่เถอะ
What about you?
แล้วเจ้าล่ะ
Me?
ข้า
I must carry out my duty as the Sword Bearer.
จะไปทำหน้าที่ของผู้ถือกระบี่
Good.
ได้
You have my permission.
ข้าอนุมัติ
We are grateful for Your Majesty's kindness.
ขอบพระทัยฝ่าบาท
Is there anything else to report?
ยังมีเรื่องอะไรอีกหรือไม่
Make your reports quick and subtle.
ถ้ามีก็พูดออกมาได้อย่างเต็มที่
Your Majesty,
ทูลฝ่าบาท
that's all for now.
ตอนนี้ไม่มีแล้วพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Great.
ดี
Then dismiss.
เช่นนั้นก็เลิกประชุม
We thank Your Majesty.
ขอบพระทัยฝ่าบาท
We shall be dismissed.
พวกกระหม่อมทูลลา
Uncle, please stay.
เสด็จอาอย่าเพิ่งไป
Uncle.
ท่านลุง
Yu'er.
อวี๋เอ๋อร์
I thought you had gone home.
เจ้ากลับบ้านไปแล้วไม่ใช่หรือ
Why are you back again?
เจ้ากลับมาทำไมอีก
Yu'er.
อวี๋เอ๋อร์
It's not safe for you to be here.
ตอนนี้ในวังอันตรายมาก
Come with me.
ไปกับลุง
Uncle.
ท่านลุง
You know His Majesty needs help,
ในเมื่อท่านรู้ว่าฝ่าบาทมีภัย
are you going to abandon him?
ยังจะทอดทิ้งพระองค์ไว้อีกหรือ
Do you think I would rather leave?
เจ้าคิดว่าข้าอยากไปอย่างนั้นหรือ
His Majesty asked me to leave.
ฝ่าบาททรงให้ข้าไป
He said
รับสั่งว่า
I would only be a liability
หากข้าอยู่ต่อ
if I stayed.
รังแต่จะถ่วงพระองค์
The master treated me with kindness,
พระองค์ทรงเมตตาข้า
I shall repay him with my loyalty.
ข้ายิ่งต้องตอบแทนด้วยคุณธรรม
Uncle.
ท่านลุง
Stay.
อยู่ต่อ
Let's help him together.
ร่วมกับข้าช่วยฝ่าบาท
Uncle, do you know
เสด็จอารู้หรือไม่
why I asked you to stay?
ว่าทำไมข้าถึงให้ท่านอยู่ต่อ
The names of the people
คนที่ข้า
I ordered Han Ding to assign to the Shencai Army
ให้หานติ้งวางแทรกไว้ในทัพเสินไฉ
(Name list of Shencai Army soldiers)
(รายชื่อแม่ทัพใหญ่คนใหม่)
are on this list.
ล้วนมีรายชื่ออยู่ในนี้ทั้งสิ้น
But I have never
แต่ข้า
promised them
ไม่เคยให้สัญญาใด ๆ
any benefit.
ต่อคนเหล่านี้
Was it your doing?
เสด็จอาเป็นคนให้สัญญาใช่หรือไม่
The Chess of Generals
สำนักหมากรุก
and Qiu Ziliang's confidants
คนสนิทของฉิวจื่อเหลียง
have been removed by Yanzhi.
ล้วนถูกเยียนจือกำจัดจนหมดสิ้น
Yanzhi's only confidant
ส่วนคนสนิทของเยียนจือ
was Yan Xiu.
ก็มีเพียงเหยียนซิวคนเดียว
The rest of them
ที่เหลือ
were your men.
ล้วนเป็นคนของท่าน
As for the Violet Bureau,
หน่วยอาภรณ์ม่วง
if Cheng Ruoyu doesn't return,
ถึงแม้เฉิงรั่วอวี๋จะไม่กลับมาอีก
it won't change the fact that Madam Jade works for you.
แต่อวี้เหนียงก็เป็นคนของท่าน
I thought
เดิมข้าคิดว่า
removing Qiu Ziliang
กำจัดฉิวจื่อเหลียงแล้ว
would disperse this corruption
ก็จะสามารถขจัดเมฆหมอก
and pave the way to a better future.
บ้านเมืองสงบสุขได้
But I never thought
แต่คิดไม่ถึงว่า
there was a man just as evil as he was.
จะมีฉีจื่อเหลียงอีกคน
Your secret has been compromised.
สุดแผนที่
Uncle.
เสด็จอา
Why not come clean while you can?
ไยไม่ชักกั้นหยั่นออกมาเล่า
How dare you
บังอาจ
block my way?
กล้าขวางทางข้า
Prince Guang and His Majesty
ฝ่าบาทกับท่านอ๋องกวง
are discussing important affairs.
กำลังหารือกันอยู่ในท้องพระโรง
I shall inform them.
กระหม่อมขอเข้าไปทูลก่อนพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Who do you think you are?
เจ้าคิดว่าตัวเองเป็นใคร
The Grand Empress Dowager is here.
ไท่หวงไท่โฮ่วเสด็จแล้ว
Greetings, Grand Empress Dowager.
ถวายบังคมไท่โฮ่ว
Official Zhang.
ใต้เท้าจาง
Official Chen.
ใต้เท้าเฉิน
Why...
นี่มัน
This is great.
ดีเลย
With the Grand Empress Dowager as our witness,
จะได้ดำเนินตามขั้นตอน
let's finish the procedures
ที่ตอนนั้นตกหล่นไป
from years ago.
ต่อหน้าพระพักตร์ไท่หวงไท่โฮ่ว
Bring it here.
นำของออกมา
Guards!
มหาดเล็ก
Your Honor,
ขุนนางทุกคน
it's been nine years
นับแต่ข้าครองราชย์
since I rose to the throne.
อยู่ในตำแหน่งมาเก้าปี
I was enraged by my disgrace.
รู้สึกอับอายโกรธแค้น
It's my goal to rid the world of evil.
คิดขจัดโจรชั่ว
But the eunuchs seized the power of the throne
หากขันทีก้าวก่ายอำนาจ
and was out of control.
ไม่อาจควบคุม
Morning Dew Rebellion's failure
การพ่ายแพ้ที่เจาลู่
caused great harm to my loyalists.
นำภัยสู่ผู้จงรัก
The true cause was my negligence.
เป็นเพราะข้าไร้สามารถ
I swear to bring down the disgraceful Qiu Ziliang with me.
วันนี้สาบานขอตายร่วมกับโจรแซ่ฉิว
But I am worried that Daxing's
หากกังวลถึงอนาคตของต้าซิง
will face a power vacancy.
แผ่นดินไม่อาจไร้ประมุข
But fortunately, my uncle Prince Guang is a man of great wisdom and vision.
เคราะห์ดีที่อาสิบสามอ๋องกวง เปี่ยมปัญญาความสามารถ
He has experienced hardship.
ผ่านอุปสรรคมาเนิ่นนาน
He carries to become a wise ruler.
มีพรสวรรค์ของผู้ยิ่งใหญ่
I shall pass my throne to Prince Guang.
ขอมอบบัลลังก์แก่อ๋องกวง
With the duty bestowed upon by the seven ancestral shrines
สืบทอดภารกิจบรรพชน
and the duty entrusted by the four seas,
รับมอบดินแดนทั้งสี่ทะเล
this edict shall be carried out by the administration.
ไปดูแลสืบต่อ
The 9th year of Tai'an,
รัชศกไท่อันที่เก้า
November 21st.
วันที่ 21 เดือน 11
This is the posthumous edict from the Late Emperor.
นี่คือพินัยกรรมของอดีตฮ่องเต้ในตอนนั้น
All we lack is the signature and verification from the Chancellery.
ขาดเพียงการลงนามรับรองจากสำนักราชเลขา
I question the authenticity of this posthumous edict.
ข้าไม่เชื่อว่าพินัยกรรมนี้เป็นของจริง
Grand Empress Dowager.
ไท่โฮ่ว
Grand Empress Dowager, have a closer look.
ไท่หวงไท่โฮ่วทอดพระเนตรให้ชัด
Since the Grand Empress Dowager
ในเมื่อไท่หวงไท่โฮ่ว
has validated the edict,
ทรงยืนยันแล้วว่าไม่ผิดพลาด
gentlemen,
เช่นนั้นใต้เท้าทุกท่าน
please give me your signatures.
ก็เชิญลงนามเถอะ
I see.
อย่างนี้นี่เอง
You've been waiting.
ท่านเฝ้ารอมาตลอด
After the Morning Dew Rebellion,
กบฏเจาลู่ในตอนนั้น
my brother wrote the posthumous edict
เสด็จพี่ทรงเขียนพินัยกรรม
to pass the throne to you.
เดิมจะมอบบัลลังก์ให้เสด็จอา
But there wasn't enough time.
แต่เพราะไม่มีเวลา
The Chancellery didn't sign the edict.
สำนักราชเลขาไม่ทันลงนาม
I was wrong.
ข้าผิดเอง
I was so wrong.
ข้าผิดไปแล้วจริง ๆ
I shouldn't have thought of you
ข้าเรียกเสด็จอา
as Qiu Ziliang's reflection.
เป็นฉิวจื่อเหลียงคนที่สองได้อย่างไร
That old fox doesn't deserve the honor.
มันยกย่องไอ้แก่นั่นเกินไป
Qiu Ziliang seized control of the Imperial Court.
ฉิวจื่อเหลียงฮุบอำนาจไว้คนเดียว
Hence, he was loathed by the world.
จนผู้คนประณามด่า
He's nothing compared to you.
ไหนเลยจะเปรียบกับเสด็จอาอ๋องกวงได้
Uncle.
เสด็จอา
You are a righteous person
สูงส่งบริสุทธิ์
whose name is sung by the people.
ชื่อเสียงดีงามเลื่องลือ
Do you think
ท่านคิดใช่หรือไม่ว่า
I've let you down?
ข้าผิดต่อท่าน
Do you think I took your throne?
แย่งบัลลังก์ของท่านไป
I used to think so.
เคยคิดเช่นนั้น
"Used to?"
เคย
But it doesn't matter now.
แต่ในตอนนี้ ไม่สำคัญแล้ว
Agreed.
ใช่
It doesn't matter now.
มันไม่สำคัญแล้ว
It's of very little significance.
ไม่สำคัญเลยสักนิด
Uncle,
เพราะเสด็จอา
that's because you could
ท่านสามารถขึ้นสืบบัลลังก์
succeed the throne
ต่อจากเสด็จพี่ได้อย่าง
righteously and peacefully
สง่างามและไร้สิ่งกีดขวางแล้ว
That will make me
ส่วนข้า
nothing more than a usurper.
ก็จะเป็นเพียงแค่คนที่ชิงบัลลังก์
Your Majesty!
ฝ่าบาท
Uncle.
เสด็จอาอ๋องกวง
It's unnecessary
ท่านไยต้อง
to act as if you care about me.
เสแสร้งแกล้งทำเช่นนี้อีก
You made a wise decision.
ใต้เท้าทุกท่านล้วนรู้สถานการณ์
The new Emperor will reward you
ความชอบใหญ่หลวงเช่นนี้
for your contribution.
ไว้ฮ่องเต้องค์ใหม่ขึ้นครองราชย์ต้องมีรางวัลแน่
I am Vice Director of Secretariat Luo Mian.
กระหม่อม หลัวเหมี่ยนซื่อหลางสำนักราชวัง
I checked the posthumous edict
ตรวจสอบพินัยกรรมอดีตฮ่องเต้
and confirmed its authenticity.
มั่นใจว่าไม่ผิดพลาด
Therefore, I gave my signature.
จึงได้ลงนาม
However,
แต่
I am sitting in this position today
กระหม่อมได้รับการส่งเสริมจากฝ่าบาท
because His Majesty promoted me.
จึงมีตำแหน่งเช่นวันนี้
I failed to uphold my loyalty.
แต่กลับไม่อาจยึดมั่นในคุณธรรม
I gained His Majesty's favor but couldn't uphold my loyalty.
รับพระมหากรุณาธิคุณแต่ไม่อาจถวายจงรัก
I am
กระหม่อม
ashamed of myself.
ละอาย
We feel ashamed.
กระหม่อมละอาย
I see.
ที่แท้
I wasn't entirely worthless.
ข้าก็ไม่ถึงกับไร้ความดี
There are some people
สุดท้ายก็ยังพอมีคนที่ไม่ยอม
that can't be bought off.
ถูกซื้อตัว
Uncle.
เสด็จอา
Only the winner is ever righteous.
นับแต่โบราณ ชนะเป็นเจ้า แพ้เป็นโจร
I lost.
ข้าแพ้แล้ว
It's an undeniable defeat.
ข้าแพ้แล้วจริง ๆ
But I
แต่ข้า
need a favor from you.
อยากขอร้องท่านสักเรื่อง
Release the backbone of our nation.
ได้โปรดละเว้นเสาหลักของแผ่นดินเหล่านี้
Let them live.
ไว้ชีวิตของพวกเขาด้วย
I beg of you.
ถือว่าข้าขอร้องท่าน
Yuan Zhi!
หยวนจื้อ
Come in.
เข้ามา
Grand Empress Dowager, please come in.
ไท่หวงไท่โฮ่วก็เชิญเสด็จเข้ามาด้วย
Yu'er.
อวี๋เอ๋อร์
It's a critical moment for Your Majesty.
ช่วงเวลาสำคัญเช่นนี้
As your Sword Bearer,
ในฐานะผู้ถือกระบี่
I must be present by your side.
หม่อมฉันไหนเลยจะไม่อยู่ข้างพระวรกายได้
Cheng Ruoyu, oh Cheng Ruoyu.
เฉิงรั่วอวี๋เอ๋ย เฉิงรั่วอวี๋
You have no idea how to cherish
เจ้าไม่เห็นแก่ความห่วงใย
your sister's effort.
ที่พี่สาวเจ้ามีให้เลย
I beg to differ.
ตรงกันข้าม
I came here because
เป็นเพราะว่า
I don't want her effort
ข้าไม่อาจรานน้ำใจของพี่ใหญ่
to be in vain.
ข้าถึงต้องมาให้ได้
Prince Guang.
ท่านอ๋องกวง
For as long as I can remember,
ที่ผ่านมา
you are the person I respect
คนที่ข้าเคารพเลื่อมใสที่สุด
the most.
ก็คือท่าน
But today,
แต่วันนี้
your crimes and actions
ทุกอย่างที่ท่านทำ
have let me down.
ทำให้ข้าผิดหวังเป็นอย่างยิ่ง
You are despicable.
ดูแคลนอย่างที่สุด
You're mistaken.
เจ้าผิดแล้ว
I'll show you what it means
วันนี้ข้าจะบอกให้เจ้ารู้ว่า
to restore order
อะไรถึงเรียกว่าก่อความวุ่นวาย
and end the chaos.
อย่างไรก็ตาม
The posthumous edict is right here.
พินัยกรรมอดีตฮ่องเต้อยู่นี่
I have read it to the officials.
เมื่อครู่ได้อ่านไปแล้ว
The Grand Empress Dowager has verified its authenticity.
ไท่หวงไท่โฮ่วก็ทรงยืนยันว่าไม่ผิดพลาด
The officials have given their signatures.
ใต้เท้าทุกท่านต่างลงนาม
Your Highness, please accept the edict.
ท่านอ๋องโปรดรับราชโองการ
This is unnecessary, Uncle.
เพื่ออะไรกัน เสด็จอา
Even without the posthumous edict,
ต่อให้ไม่มีพินัยกรรม
the throne
บัลลังก์นี้
will still be yours.
ข้าก็ยังคงมอบให้ท่านอยู่ดี
I don't want it.
ข้าไม่ต้องการ
You don't want it?
ท่านไม่ต้องการ
Of course.
ท่านย่อมไม่ต้องการอยู่แล้ว
The throne was yours
เพราะว่าบัลลังก์นี้
all along.
มันเป็นของท่านแต่เดิม
But I
ส่วนข้า
was nothing but a usurper.
เป็นแค่คนที่ชิงมันมาเท่านั้น
I have no right
ไหนเลยมีคุณสมบัติ
to give it to you as mine.
ที่จะมาบอกว่ายกให้ท่านได้
Am I wrong?
หรือว่าไม่ใช่
When I was little,
ตอนเด็ก ๆ
I had often dreamed
ข้ามักจะฝันเห็น
that I was riding a dragon in the sky.
ตัวข้าขี่มังกรบินอยู่บนฟ้า
I told my mother about the dream.
ข้าเล่าเรื่องนี้ให้ท่านแม่ข้าฟัง
She told me
นางกลับกำชับข้าว่า
not to let another soul know.
ห้ามเล่าให้ใครฟังเด็ดขาด
Otherwise,
หาไม่
I would be in grave danger.
อาจนำมาซึ่งภัยถึงชีวิต
Even as a child,
ที่แท้เจ้า
you had planned to seize the throne.
ก็มีใจคิดชิงบัลลังก์ตั้งแต่เด็ก
When I was little,
ตอนเด็ก
I fell ill.
ข้าเคยป่วยหนักครั้งหนึ่ง
I was lying in my bed
ข้านอนซมอยู่บนที่นอน
and barely conscious.
หลับใหลไม่ได้สติ
Then a ray of light
ทันใดก็มีแสง
shined upon me.
สาดส่องมาที่ร่างข้า
I jumped up
ข้าดีใจจนลุกขึ้น
and greeted it,
ประสานมือคำนับ
as if I were an Emperor who was greeting his officers.
ประหนึ่งเหนือหัวปฏิบัติตนต่อขุนนาง
My mother was scared speechless.
ท่านแม่ข้าตกใจจนวิญญาณแทบหลุดจากร่าง
That's because
เพราะว่า
my brother saw it.
เสด็จพี่มาเห็นเข้าพอดี
But my brother wasn't mad at me.
แต่เสด็จพี่หาได้พิโรธ
He touched my back
กลับทรงหัวเราะ
and talked to me with a smile.
ลูบหลังข้าแล้วตรัสว่า
"Brother,
น้องพี่
you are truly..."
สมเป็น
"The prodigy of our family."
ยอดคนในตระกูล
I have forgotten the dreams I had
ความฝันมากมายตอนเด็ก
as a child.
ล้วนลืมไปจนสิ้น
But those words
แต่คำพูดนี้
have never left my memory.
กลับจารึกแน่นอยู่ในใจข้ามาตลอด
But our late father
แต่ตอนเสด็จพ่อยังทรงพระชนม์
loved you the most.
ทรงรักท่านที่สุด
The royalty is a family of cruelty.
ต่างพูดกันว่าคนในราชวงศ์ล้วนแล้งน้ำใจ
It's especially so for the sons of the Qi family.
โดยเฉพาะลูกชายในตระกูลฉีของเรา
To seize the throne,
เพื่อบัลลังก์
parents were killed or exiled,
ฆ่าได้ทั้งพ่อแม่
siblings fought in countless power struggles.
พี่น้องฆ่ากันกลาดเกลื่อนไปหมด
The ambition for great power
ความกระหายในอำนาจ
flows in our veins.
ได้แทรกซึมอยู่ในทุกอณูของสายเลือดเรา
It makes us restless all the time.
ทำให้พวกเราก่อความวุ่นวายได้ไม่หยุด
Do I want to be the Emperor?
ข้าอยากเป็นฮ่องเต้หรือไม่
Yes.
เคยอยาก
Did I have the opportunity?
ข้ามีโอกาสหรือไม่
Sure.
มี
You finally admitted it.
ในที่สุดเจ้าก็ยอมรับ
Right Minister "Thirteen" of the Chess of Generals Camp
โย่วเซี่ยงสิบสามแห่งสำนักหมากรุก
was my double.
คือตัวแทนของข้า
I had numerous chances
ข้ามีโอกาสนับครั้งไม่ถ้วน
to take your life with Qiu Ziliang's hands.
สามารถยืมมือฉิวจื่อเหลียงฆ่าเจ้าเสีย
I had discovered Zheng Wu's background long ago.
ชาติกำเนิดของเจิ้งอู่ ข้ารู้ตั้งแต่แรก
I had plenty of chances
ข้ามีโอกาสมากมาย
to expose her.
ที่จะเปิดโปงนาง
The royal retainers of Zhenwu escorted Ninghe back to the Capital.
ขุนนางเมืองเจิ้นอู๋ คุ้มกันหนิงเหอกลับเมืองหลวง
Han Yue
หานเยว่
was devoted to accomplish
ต้องการจะทำตามรับสั่งของ
the Late Emperor's dying wish
อดีตฮ่องเต้ให้สำเร็จ
and help me seize the throne.
ช่วยให้ข้าได้ครองราชย์
Cheng Xi was
เฉิงซี
my elder sister from a different father.
เป็นพี่สาวคนละพ่อกับข้า
As for Yanzhi...
ส่วนเยียนจือ
was the descendant of my old acquaintance.
เป็นทายาทสหายเก่าของข้า
You had been using my sister
แปลว่าที่ผ่านมา
all this time.
ท่านหลอกใช้พี่สาวข้ามาตลอด
You used her for your revenge.
หลอกใช้นางล้างแค้น
You used her to get rid of Qiu Ziliang
กำจัดฉิวจื่อเหลียง
so you could command the Camp,
ควบคุมสำนักหมากรุก
you tricked her into thinking
ให้นางหลงเข้าใจว่า
you felt guilty for the Wang family's fate,
ท่านละอายใจต่อตระกูลหวัง
that you wanted revenge!
ความจริงเพื่อล้างแค้น
As for Your Majesty,
ส่วนฝ่าบาท
you were at death's doorstep many times.
หลายครั้งที่ประชวรหนัก
You wanted me to succeed the throne.
ต้องการสละบัลลังก์ให้ผู้อื่น
All the stars were aligned.
เวลา สถานที่ ผู้คน
I have many chances
ข้ามีโอกาสนับครั้งไม่ถ้วน
to get what I had always pursued.
ที่จะทำให้ความปรารถนาข้าเป็นจริง
But I
แต่ข้า
refused it.
ก็ทิ้งมัน
The Dragon Throne is here.
บัลลังก์มังกรอยู่ตรงนั้น
I can sit on it.
ข้าสามารถนั่งได้
And if I do,
ข้านั่งแล้ว
that is my power.
นั่นคืออำนาจ
I can sit on it.
บัลลังก์มังกรอยู่ตรงนั้น
And if I refuse to sit on it,
ข้านั่งได้ แต่ไม่นั่ง
that's morality.
นั่นคือคุณธรรม
It's easy to give in to power.
คล้อยตามอำนาจนั้นง่าย
But dying for morality is a tough decision.
ผดุงคุณธรรมนั้นกลับยาก
It was the same as my brother.
เหมือนที่เสด็จพี่ปฏิบัติต่อข้าตอนนั้น
He could have taken my life.
เดิมเขาสามารถฆ่าข้าได้
He could have easily punished me
ด้วยความผิดฐานทรยศ
for my crime of treason.
สำหรับเขาแล้วเป็นเรื่องที่ง่ายดาย
But he didn't do it.
แต่เขาไม่ทำ
He smiled and
หากกลับยิ้มแย้ม
praised me.
ชมเชยข้า
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
Don't you think
พระองค์ก็คิดว่า
the emperors are heartless and the royal family is without compassion?
เหนือหัวไร้น้ำใจ เชื้อพระวงศ์ไร้คุณธรรมหรือ
But I...
แต่ข้า
No!
ไม่
No matter how low I stoop,
ข้าไม่มีวัน
I will never hurt
และไม่มีทางที่จะลงมือ
my own family.
ต่อญาติพี่น้องของตน
Not to mention
ที่สำคัญ
you are my brother's son.
พระองค์เป็นลูกชายของเสด็จพี่
You are my nephew.
เป็นหลานชายแท้ ๆ ของข้า
Your Highness.
ท่านอ๋อง
Shut it.
หุบปาก
We had planned for years.
พวกเราวางแผนกันมาตั้งนาน
But...
ตอนนี้
Shut it.
หุบปาก
Your Highness!
ท่านอ๋อง
Scram!
ไป
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
There is something
มีวาจาประโยคหนึ่ง
that I had brought up many times in the past.
ก่อนหน้านี้ข้าเคยพูดมาหลายครั้ง
Now,
ตอนนี้
I'll say it one last time.
ข้าจะขอพูดเป็นครั้งสุดท้าย
You will always be my Emperor.
พระองค์เป็นฝ่าบาทของกระหม่อมตลอดไป
Uncle.
เสด็จอา
Sir.
ใต้เท้า
I was ordered by His Majesty
ฝ่าบาททรงมีรับสั่ง
to summon you.
ให้มาเชิญใต้เท้าหลี่
Who let her in?
ใครให้นางมา
His Majesty will see to it.
ฝ่าบาททรงรู้ว่าต้องทำเช่นไร
Greetings, Your Majesty.
ถวายบังคมฝ่าบาท
Your Majesty, are you hurt?
ฝ่าบาททรงไม่เป็นไรนะเพคะ
I have an announcement to make.
ข้ามีเรื่องหนึ่งจะประกาศ
I want all the officers present in the main hall.
เรียกขุนนางทั้งหมดมาที่ท้องพระโรง
♪Life is a dream how long do happy times last♪
♪ชีวิตล่องลอยดุจฝัน เคยสุขกี่ครั้ง♪
♪The sword can't break this karma♪
♪ชักดาบฟันฟาด กลับมิอาจสะบั้นเหตุและผล♪
♪Look how blurry and lonely the world is♪
♪มองฟ้ามองดินล้วนไม่ยินไม่แยแส♪
♪Still can't let go of this life as time goes by♪
♪ตะวันรุ่งจันทราโรย ชีพนี้ยังคงน่าถนอม♪
♪Even the iron and golden dagger-axe cannot extinguish the fire in my heart♪
♪ควบอาชาพร้อมอาวุธ มิอาจหยุดไฟในทรวง♪
♪Remembering the past and letting time while away♪
♪คิดถึงฝันในวันเก่า นานเท่านาน ยังคงเจ็บ♪
♪The past is in front of you♪
♪อดีตพลันไหลผ่านสองตา♪
♪Forgetting while piecing it together♪
♪ทางหนึ่งเพียรลืม อีกทางเพียรจำ♪
♪Like when I sincerely put my hands together♪
♪หากข้าประกบมือประนมกร♪
♪I only wish that you can be saved♪
♪ไหว้วอนให้เจ้าได้หลุดพ้น♪
♪The past is in front of you♪
♪อดีตพลันไหลผ่านสองตา♪
♪Forgetting while piecing it together♪
♪ทางหนึ่งเพียรลืม อีกทางเพียรจำ♪
♪Like when I sincerely put my hands together♪
♪หากข้าประกบมือประนมกร♪
♪I only wish that you can be saved♪
♪ไหว้วอนให้เจ้าได้หลุดพ้น♪